You’ve probably seen the headlines.
Uber burnt through its AI budget in 4 months.
Another company spent $500 million in just one.
Token costs have even gone “far
beyond the costs of the employees”.
Yet, all these companies tried to
spend as much as possible on tokens.
Companies have wildly overspent on
tokens, and are now cutting back.
But, all of this is especially weird, because
tokens aren’t actually getting more expensive.
They’re getting cheaper.
The price of a single token has
fallen by about 90% since 2023.
But, AI spend keeps going up.
So what’s going on?
Why did cheaper tokens make
AI more expensive than ever?
Something’s happened that may have
changed the AI industry for good.
It feels like just a few months ago,
companies were pushing every employee
to spend as many tokens as possible.
Many were calling it… “tokenmaxxing”,
literally meaning 'maximizing token usage’.
You can probably see where this is going…
At Uber, engineers were given
access to Claude Code and Cursor,
and by March 2026, 84% of Uber's developers
were classified as agentic coding users.
Then, Uber placed a cap on employee AI spend,
after going through their entire
AI budget in just 4 months.
[Praveen Neppalli Naga, Chief Technology
Officer, Uber]: "I'm back to the drawing
board because the budget I thought
I would need is blown away already”.
Even worse, Uber’s COO and president said
[Andrew Macdonald, Uber President/COO] “If
you’re not actually able to draw a direct line
to how [many] useful features and functionality
you’re shipping to your users, that trade becomes
harder to justify. That link is not there yet.”
But, this list goes on and on.
In 30 days, Meta workers reportedly
ran through 60 trillion Claude tokens.
Microsoft encouraged employees to use
different AI tools, but is now pushing
everyone back to GitHub Copilot.
Even though this is framed as
“consolidation”, most see it as cost cutting.
Amazon set targets for more than 80%
of developers to use AI each week.
They even had an AI leaderboard, KiroRank,
which tracked AI token use among employees.
Employees then began inflating their scores
through “tokenmaxxing”. Basically giving AI
useless tasks to increase token use.
KiroRank was then taken offline.
Amazon’s Senior Vice President said “Please
don’t use AI just for the sake of using AI,”.
An even stranger case is NVIDIA.
About a month later, an NVIDIA executive said
[Bryan Catanzaro, vice president of applied
deep learning, NVIDIA]: “For my team, the cost of
compute is far beyond the costs of the employees”.
Another anonymous AI client burned through $500
million on AI in just one month, because they
didn’t set limits on employee licenses.
Shopify, Spotify, ServiceNow,
and Roku all mentioned in their earnings
calls that AI has become a major pressure
point on operating expenses.
Not only is the cost spiking,
but so are the problems.
One being “code churn”.
Aka lines of code deleted versus added.
Alex Circei, the CEO of Waydev, said that
managers are seeing code acceptance rates of 80%
to 90%, aka the AI code developers approve and
keep, but don’t consider the amount of revision
engineers have to do in the following weeks.
“Which drives the real-world acceptance rate
down between 10% and 30% of generated code.”
GitClear found in a report that AI tools
did make developers more productive,
but the amount of code churn they had to do was
2.2x greater than their productivity increase.
Faros AI found that, based on two years of
customer data, code churn had increased by 861%.
Another study of 2,444 companies found that
for every dollar a company spends on AI tokens,
$0.44 is used to fix bugs generated by AI,
$0.27 to rewrite AI-produced code, and $0.11
is consumed in review and merge delays.
“In other words, behind every dollar
of AI procurement cost lies
nearly 80% in hidden losses.”
People are calling this the “Tokenpocalypse”.
Companies tied token consumption to
productivity and output, but all
that happened was way higher costs.
They all fell into the same
problem: Goodhart's Law.
When a measure becomes a target,
it ceases to be a good measure.
Silicon Valley, collectively, just
went through a very strange experiment.
Goldman Sachs reported that companies
are “overrunning their initial budgets
for inference by orders of magnitude.”
And what makes all this even stranger,
is that token cost, has gone down.
90% since 2023.
By other metrics, they’ve dropped by 280x.
But simultaneously AI spend is exploding,
by an estimated 320%.
Worldwide IT spending is expected to hit
$6.31 trillion in 2026, up 13.5% year over year.
More than the entire annual GDP of the UK.
U.S. enterprises have become more
cost-conscious in their AI spending,
and this has caused another surprising
phenomenon, more on that later.
More importantly, why isn’t more token
usage converting into better results?
Why does it feel like AI
is getting more expensive?
Before we can answer this, what
does “token” actually mean?
LLMs like ChatGPT don’t understand language. They
can’t read what you say, see an image you send,
or hear the audio you speak.
“The word darkness, for example,
would be split into two tokens, “dark”
and “ness,” with each token bearing a
numerical representation, such as 217 and
655. The model processes these input tokens,
generates its response as tokens and then
translates it to the user’s expected format.”
According to NVIDIA: “The goal is to achieve
the fastest processing time and lowest cost per
token to optimize AI infrastructure
and maximize revenue generation”.
Keep that in mind, because something that’s
happening now, makes that claim rather ironic.
And as a disclaimer I’m not
an AI expert, not even close.
But what I am extremely interested in is the
business side, and why many businesses
have done a 180 on their token spend.
There are a few factors to this.
The first is that tokens consumed
don’t scale linearly with productive output.
A study by Jellyfish found that larger token
budgets did result in more pull requests,
aka, proposed changes to a shared codebase,
but ten times the tokens,
produced about 2 times the output.
“Tokens, in this sense, behave less like
a linear input and more like rocket fuel.
Going faster is possible, but it requires
exponentially more resources to do so.”
Another problem, one that’s
perhaps most surprising,
comes from the more advanced reasoning models.
Remember what NVIDIA said about “fastest
processing time”? Well, that’s
where we run into a problem.
Claude Opus, GPT o3, the ones that can
tackle harder problems, spend minutes
or even hours thinking to solve a problem.
“Reasoning AI models, the latest advancement in
LLMs, can tackle more complex queries by treating
tokens differently than before. Here, in addition
to input and output tokens, the model generates
a host of reasoning tokens over minutes or hours
as it thinks about how to solve a given problem.”
The power of these things, is pretty unbelievable.
So powerful, that the US Government has
issued an export control on Claude Fable,
due to national security risks.
But, the more powerful models have
caused an… interesting problem to occur.
If you ask your friend “What’s 1+1”,
they’ll probably say “2” straight away.
But, imagine if they stopped,
and really deeply thought about it
for 30 seconds, and then said “2”.
You’d think “You already know the answer,
why’d you think so hard about it”.
That’s basically what’s happening.
AI right now has a bit of a reasoning
problem. Or, rather, an inefficiency problem.
If you ask some, not all, but some of the
state-of-the-art reasoning LLMs
this question, they will stop,
break down the question, deliberate over
it, and may even take 10 or 20 seconds.
They can break tasks into smaller
subtasks of a larger problem. Greater
potential output, but more tokens consumed.
What’s weird, is the “lighter” AI models,
can do this immediately, not that they inherently
do math, but based on training and probability,
the right response to your query is “2”.
[Firat Elbey, Principal Product Manager]:“Every
unnecessary reasoning cycle increases latency,
compounds infrastructure costs, and consumes
energy. Recent analyses suggest that unnecessary
prompt verbosity alone costs tens of millions of
dollars in excess computation annually”.
So even though all those engineers get
encouraged to use more AI, if the way they’re
used isn’t extremely specific and intentional
to the task, it can be totally off.
Complex task to a low-level model?
More problems, inadequate results.
Easy task to a high-level model? Longer
task duration, overconsumption
of tokens, inefficient results.
[Firat Elbey, Principal Product Manager]:
”While these are powerful tools,
they're often deployed indiscriminately across
a wide variety of tasks, including countless
queries that likely require no reasoning at all
— and this inefficiency has real consequences.”
All of this compounds even more,
when we look at Agentic AI.
This is when you give an AI model a goal,
and a collection of tools. Running code,
searching the web, writing files,
calling APIs, and it runs autonomously.
But, while chatting is a single call and response,
an agent goes in a loop
until it deems the task done.
Look at the result, think again,
do the next thing, repeat. Lots
of small steps, lots of tokens used.
But, this gets more expensive because
every time it loops back to “think”,
it re-reads all the context so far.
This is the Agentic Loop Multiplier, and
it’s what’s driving up a lot of cost.
Goldman Sachs forecasts agentic AI could drive
a 24-fold increase in token consumption by 2030,
reaching 120 quadrillion tokens per month.
With this in mind, you can see how easy it would
be for employees to waste tokens on… nothing.
Especially when they’re given a blanket rule
to “spend more tokens!”
Again: Goodhart's Law.
More tokens, doesn’t always mean better results.
But, something doesn’t quite add up.
We still come back to the question: Why
did cheaper tokens cause a spike in cost?
Well, this isn’t actually anything new.
Not only that, have you noticed how almost
all AI companies have recently
changed their business model?
We might be moving into a totally
new stage in the AI lifecycle.
If you haven’t subscribed yet,
consider subscribing. We’re on the road to
1 million and are over 90% there! Thank you.
Ironically, cheaper tokens,
are what drove more cost.
As cost of production decreases,
demand and consumption often increase.
The Jevons paradox.
The more efficient
you make a resource the greater the demand for it.
This gives us crucial context for
a major change in the world of AI.
Have you noticed that many of these platforms have
changed from subscriptions to token use pricing?
There’s still subscriptions, of course,
but these just give you an allocation
of tokens, which you can use daily.
The high spending engineers and companies,
will likely be setting token budgets,
rather than a fixed subscription rate.
We’re experiencing what I think is a major market
transition we’ve seen in all kinds of industries.
Streaming services appear,
charging a low subscription,
gaining market adoption, then raising
prices and introducing new revenue streams.
Delivery apps did the same thing,
losing money to get market penetration,
then changing to focus on profit.
AI is doing the same thing, except changing
the model to charge based on token use.
Since spring 2025, every major AI agent
company — Cursor, Vercel's V0, Replit,
Lovable — almost simultaneously moved to
token-based billing, shrank or eliminated free
tiers, and pushed overage charges onto users.
[Christian Klein, CEO, SAP] "It would be foolish
to still charge a subscription base, because AI is
so powerful that it will automate a lot of tasks”.
It’s not just AI models either.
Just a few years ago, most software as a service
companies used to use seat-based pricing.
But with AI agents, that’s largely disappearing.
Hence why so many are overhauling
their entire business model.
We’re at a tipping point with AI right now.
When reviewing spending data from
over 50,000 US companies, Ramp,
a U.S. corporate spending management platform,
found DeepSeek, the Chinese AI, is rising fast.
“Past regulars on this list have been
Silicon Valley favorites like Figma and
Fireworks AI—this is the first time a
Chinese model company has topped it.”
DeepSeek’s V4-Pro model will cost $3.48 for
1 million tokens of output; by comparison,
OpenAI and Anthropic charge $30 and $25
respectively for the same amount of work.
Another Chinese AI Kimi
cost $4 per million tokens.
Note that this is just price,
not quality of model output.
But not only are token prices
from Chinese AI cheaper, but their
models are surpassing US ones in downloads.
Does this mean total use? I don’t think so.
Anthropic and OpenAI are still leading
corporate adoption at 34.4% and 32.3%,
but DeepSeek is securing a place
as the cost-effective alternative.
I do think we’re moving from one stage of
AI to another, even if it takes a while.
Companies are becoming more critical of their
AI spend, and how it translates into output.
In a lot of cases, it’s just the
same results, but with more cost.
Once again, humans are underrated.
[Firat Elbey, Principal Product Manager]:
“Efficient AI can learn from
human cognition's adaptive
resource allocation — knowing
when to engage deep processing,
not just how to process deeply.”
[Whizy Kim, Techbrew]: “unlike AI,
human workers can actually be held
accountable for their mistakes”
What I find particularly funny, is actually
Microsoft, pivoting back to Copilot.
They’ve had nothing but problems with
this thing, and managed to annoy seemingly
all 365 customers… and Windows users.
Click here to learn the rest of the story.